Good morning. Today's דף daf is צדי ב, tzadi-beis, and we pick
up at the top and we are dealing with the question in
the משנה Mishnah that the משנה Mishnah we learned yesterday said that
if you have a basket filled with fruit and you take it
out from a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid from like a house into
the street, a רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, even if most of the
basket's on the outside as long as part of it is still
on the inside, you have not yet carried it. Now the simple
sense of that is this idea that the basket makes it all
one and you don't look at the fruit individually. You basically look
at it as a fruit basket and not like separate items of
fruit. So even if a whole fruit is on the outside, it
doesn't matter. It's now defined as part of the fruit basket. And
that is the position of אגד כלי שמי אגד, egged kli shmei
egged, that being bound in a vessel is like bound makes it
one unit. However, there are other reads of this משנה Mishnah that
downplay the idea of the basket, read it that the—not individual fruits
are fully outside, but it's very long fruits which the most of
the fruit is outside and really—and you know, really minimize the חידוש
chidush of this משנה. Mishnah. So we continue with this debate right
now, top of צדי ב עמוד א, tzadi-beis amud aleph, four lines
from the top. וכן אמר רבא, V'chein amar Rava, and רבא Rava
said similarly, לא שנו אלא בקופה מלאה קישואין ודלועין. lo shanu ela
b'kuppah meleiah kishu'in v'dulu'in. Our משנה Mishnah is talking about a basket
filled with like gourds and cucumbers. So even the—even the entirety of
one fruit is not on the outside. אבל מלאה חרדל, Aval meleiah
chardal, if it's filled with mustard seed, meaning in fruits that you
know, when part of the basket is on the outside, whole fruits
are on the outside, in that case, חייב. chayiv. You would be
חייב. chayiv. You look at the individual fruits, you do not look
at the basket as a whole. אלמא קסבר, Alma kasavar, you see
that he's of the opinion, אגד כלי לא שמי אגד, egged kli
lo shmei egged, that being bound in a vessel is not considered
being bound, does not make it one unit of a fruit basket,
and you look at the individual fruits. Again, a hard read of
the משנה. Mishnah. אביי אמר, Abaye amar, אביי Abaye says, אפילו מלאה
חרדל, afilu meleiah chardal, even if it's filled with mustard seed, פטור
patur you're exempt. Even though a thousand mustard seeds are on the
outside, as long as part of the basket is on the inside,
you're exempt. אלמא קסבר, Alma kasavar, you see he is of the
opinion, אגד כלי שמי אגד, egged kli shmei egged, being bound by
a basket is considered being bound, makes it one unit. So now
the גמרא Gemara says, קם אביי בשיטתיה דרבא קם רבא בשיטתיה דאביי.
kam Abaye b'shittasei d'Rava, kam Rava b'shittasei d'Abaye. The גמרא Gemara had
a tradition, it doesn't even quote any particular statement that they made,
but has a tradition that each side reversed their position, that you
know, אביי Abaye wound up taking רבא's Rava position and רבא Rava
wound up taking אביי's Abaye position. So, so they're still disagreeing, but
now on the other side of the argument. Okay, so this way
רבא Rava is the one that says אגד כלי שמי אגד. egged
kli shmei egged. This is important for הלכה halacha because we almost
always rule like רבא Rava against אביי. Abaye. And now רבא Rava
is saying the simple read of the משנה Mishnah that אגד כלי
שמי אגד. egged kli shmei egged. Now the גמרא Gemara says,
ורמי דאביי אדאביי ורמי דרבא אדרבא. v'remi d'Abaye ad'Abaye, v'remi d'Rava ad'Rava.
Now I'll show you a contradiction of אביי Abaye on his own
statement and רבא Rava on his own statement. And תוספות Tosafot says,
you know, since רבא Rava and אביי Abaye each held both sides
of the argument at different times, thank you very much, how do
you know that anything is a contradiction? How do you know whether
it's from you know, their early position or their revised position? So
תוספות Tosafot just says, if you look at this brief תוספות, Tosafot,
two lines—three lines from the top,
ורמי דאביי דאביי קים להו לש"ס דהאי מילתא דמייתי איתמר בתר דהדר
בהו. v'remi d'Abaye d'Abaye, kim lehu l'shas d'hai milsa d'maisi itmar basar
d'hadar behu. We know that the following quote we're going to have
אביי Abaye and רבא Rava came out after they reversed themselves, after—when
they had adopted their second position. Okay, so again, it's quite interesting
how much of what's going on here is not based on any
direct evidence. Meaning the assertion that they reversed their position, we're not
quoting any evidence, we just know that. The idea that the next
statement came late, not early. Okay, and now we're going to show
that there's a contradiction. What's the contradiction? Remember, according to the way
we're having it now, רבא Rava holds that אגד כלי שמי אגד,
egged kli shmei egged, it's all one basket, and אביי Abaye holds
that they're individual. Let's see where it seems that they've contradicted themselves.
Okay, דאיתמר, d'itmar, it was taught,
המוציא פירות לרשות הרבים, hamotzi peiros l'reshus harabbim, if you bring out
fruit into the public domain. אביי אמר ביד חייב, Abaye amar b'yad
chayiv, in your hand you're חייב, chayiv, בכלי פטור bikli patur in
a vessel you're פטור. patur. Now read simply, this makes no sense.
What, if I'm holding an apple and I walk out, I'm חייב,
chayiv, but if I have my apple in a basket and I
walk out, I'm פטור? patur? So the assumption here means is that
we're talking about exactly a scenario like this. Partly inside, partly outside.
So what does it mean the hand? It means here I am,
I'm standing in my house, right, here's my apple, this table is
the רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, and I do that. I took it
out with my—only with my hand, right, not with the rest of
my body. That's the first משנה. Mishnah. We're going to get to
that. Okay, so am I חייב chayiv or not? Is it considered
to be in the רשות הרבים reshus harabbim or because my body
is in the house, I'm פטור? patur? The idea of the basket
is exactly our scenario. The basket part is out, but part of
the basket is in. Do you look at it as one unit
or not one unit? So the same question about the basket, if
part of the basket is in, we could look at my person,
my body is in but my hand is out, does it go
by where the fruit is or does it go where—by where my
body is? In the basket, does it go by where the basket
is or does it go by where the fruit is? Okay, so
here,
yes.
Well, but if you—it's a qualitative question. What if you have an
itty-bitty basket that's just barely the size of
the—
Then you won’t—it’ll be hard to find a נפקא מינא. nafka mina.
It’ll be hard to find a case where you have one without
the other. But that—but okay, but we’re looking for an interesting case.
And how about a little basket, how is that different than just
having a fruit?
It wouldn’t be. There are cases where
it wouldn’t be an interesting question, but it’s an interesting question when
the basket is bigger than the fruit.
The basket, so
that’s what they’re talking about. Exactly. Okay, exactly.
Quantitative rather than qualitative.
Right. I mean, it’s a question of finding the scenario which makes
for an interesting question. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, so
here’s the case. So let’s read it again. המציא פירות לרשות הרבים,
hamotzi peirot lereshut harabbim, you bring fruit out into רשות הרבים. reshut
harabbim. אביי אמר ביד, Abaye amar beyad, if you stuck your hand
out but you’re in the house, חייב. chayav. בכלי, bikli, if the
vessel went out and part of it is out, part of it
is in, פטור, patur, you’re exempt. Which means אגד כלי שמיה אגד
eged kli shemei eged is one unit. So even if part of
the vessel is in, then you’re exempt. רבא אמר, Rava amar, now
רבא Rava says the reverse. ביד פטור, beyad patur, if you stick
it out with your hand you’re exempt, בכלי
חייב, bikli chayav, because part your body is on the inside, בכלי,
bikli, but if it’s in the vessel, חייב, chayav, even though part
of the—even though part of the basket is on the inside, since
some of the fruit is on the outside you’re חייב, chayav, which
means אגד כלי eged kli is לא שמיה אגד. lo shemei eged.
So here רבא Rava is taking—אביי Abaye is taking the opinion that
it is one unit, רבא Rava is taking the opinion that it’s
not, and that’s opposite their later position on this matter. So how
do you deal with this? So the גמרא Gemara says איפכא, ipcha,
fine, alright, reverse their—reverse what they were saying. Okay. Fine. So either
you could have said it was someone earlier went earlier time when
they held these earlier positions or you reverse the names. Okay, so
reverse second part the second yes presumably the second ברייתא, Baraita, the
second teaching, you reverse the names of אביי Abaye and רבא. Rava.
So now it’s important להלכה lehalacha because now what the גמרא Gemara
is saying is not only two halachic points now that רבא Rava
is saying. One is אגד כלי שמיה אגד, eged kli shemei eged,
you look at the basket as one unit, you don’t look at
it as fruit in a basket, you look at it as a
fruit basket, and therefore you go by the whole basket. But now
we have another statement of, so fine, if part of the vessel’s
in, part is out, you’re exempt. But the other part of רבא’s
Rava statement, which now has been sort of changed to רבא, Rava,
it was אביי, Abaye, part the other part of his statement is,
if you are standing in the house and you stick your hand
out, right, that you’re actually going to be חייב, chayav, right, that’s
the other part of the statement. By the basket, part of it
is inside gets you off the hook. But by you standing inside
and sticking your hand out, you’re going to be חייב. chayav. Says
Michael, what about the first משנה? Mishnah? Well, the גמרא Gemara realized
the question too. So let’s take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
So the גמרא Gemara says, it says like this, it says ביד
חייב, beyad chayav, so I don’t get it. The basket, fine, that’s
one unit, and if part is inside you’re exempt. But with a
hand, if you’re standing inside and you stick your hand outside you’re
חייב, chayav, that’s—that’s the very first משנה Mishnah of this מסכת, Masechet,
פשט בעל הבית ידו לחוץ, pashat baal habayit yado lachutz, you,
you’re in the house, you stuck your hand out with the loaf
of bread to the poor person, right, ונטל העני מתוכה, venatal he'ani
mitocha, and the poor person takes from your hand, או שנתן לתוכה
והכניס, o shenatan letocha vehichnis, the reverse, he put in your hand
and you pulled in, שניהם פטורין, sheneihem peturin, they’re exempt. So it’s
exactly this case. You’re in the house, you stuck your hand outside
with the bread, and you’re exempt, it’s not like you put it
in the רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim, right, he has to take it
from your hand and only then is he חייב. chayav. So isn’t
that exactly against this idea? So the גמרא Gemara says התם למעלה
מג' הכא למטה מג'. hatam lemala migimmel, hacha lemata migimmel. Oh, no,
the reason there you’re exempt is not because—this is the way רש"י
Rashi explains it very nicely, he says, the reason you’re exempt is
not because we see the fruit as still in the house because
your body is in the house. The reason you’re exempt is the
fruit is really outside. If I asked you where’s the fruit, it’s
a hundred percent outside. So why are you exempt? Because it hasn’t
been put down on the ground. But that’s a separate issue. The
issue of the basket is where is the fruit? Do you say,
so there you say, the fruit isn’t outside. It’s one unit with
the basket and therefore it’s part in, part out. That’s its location.
So then by the way you understand why the basket is different
than the hand. By the basket it’s an object, so you can
look at it as a single object and part in part out.
If my hand with the apple’s outside, the apple is the object,
I, my hand and me, I’m the person, right? We don’t look
at the apple as one with me, like the apple’s now an
extension of me. The apple’s always distinct from me. So if you
ask where is the apple when it’s in my hand, it’s outside.
It’s not like I am an apple-bearing person and it’s our one
thing, right? There’s an apple in my hand and the apple is
outside. So therefore it is location-wise, it’s outside. But we have a
problem: it’s not on the ground. Okay, that’s a different issue. So
if my hand is within three, anything within three is considered on
the ground, then I’m חייב. chayav. When it’s above three, then the
poor person has to take it off of my hand. So it’s
a very nice point, and רש"י Rashi says it very clearly.
רש"י Rashi says התם למעלה מג', hatam lemala migimmel, four lines before
the משנה, Mishnah, וטעמא משום דלא נח. vetaama mishum d'lo nach. The
problem with there, the apple in my hand sticking out of the
house, is because it hasn’t come to rest, it hasn’t been put
down. ולא משום אגד גופיה, velo mishum eged gufeih, not because of
its connection to my body. So if you’re dealing with a fruit
basket, you could say it’s one unit, it’s not fully outside. An
apple in my hand, it is fully outside. It’s a separate question
of has it been put on the ground or not. Okay, so
that is the end of that question. In a very interesting one
about the fruit in the basket and the distinction between the basket,
the fruit in the basket, and the fruit in my hand and
going back to issues of the first משנה Mishna, *Mishnah*. Now we
turn to the next משנה Mishna, *Mishnah*, which is
again a very important point about carrying and also as you'll see
really extremely important about almost all מלאכות Melachot, *melachot* of שבת Shabbat
*Shabbat*. So let's take a look. המוציא בין בימינו בין בשמאלו *hamotzi
bein b'yimino bein b'smolo*, whether you take out something whether you're holding
it in your right hand or your left hand, בתוך חיקו *b'toch
heiko*, you're holding it in your chest, like I don't know it's
something that's somehow in some clothing and it's against your chest, או
על כתפיו *o al kteifav*, or you're holding it on your shoulders,
חייב Chayav *hayav*. In all those cases you're חייב Chayav *hayav*. שכן
משא בני קהת Bnei Kehat *shekein masa b'nei Kehat*, that is the
way when the בני קהת Bnei Kehat, *b'nei Kehat*, you know, carried
the משכן Mishkan. *Mishkan* in they, you know, the whole משכן Mishkan.
*Mishkan* was taken apart and then they carried the vessels, so therefore
they would carry, I mean, most things you would think they would
carry on the shoulders, right? Because קהת *Kehat* would carry the ארון
Aron *aron*, they would carry the primary vessels. So what does it
mean they're also carrying in their hand and on their chest? So
Rashi quotes a famous גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, a ירושלמי *Yerushalmi*, if you
look at Rashi, שכן משא בני קהת Bnei Kehat, *shekein masa b'nei
Kehat*, so Rashi says ובכתף ישאו *uv'kateif yisau*. Okay, so maybe that's
only really elaborating on the last one about the shoulder. או בימין
ושמאל וחיק *o b'yamin u'smol v'heik*, and right hand, left hand, or
in your chest, אורח ארעא *orah ar'a*, that you don't need a
special פסוק pasuk. *pasuk*, that's a normal way of carrying things. Pretty
funny you'd also think shoulder is a normal way, but it depends
what you're carrying. Okay, anyway, ובשם רבנו יצחק בר יהודה מצאתי *u'v'shem
Rabbeinu Yitzhak bar Yehuda matzati* שאמר בשם רב האי *she-amar b'shem Rav
Hai* שמפורש בש"ס ירושלמי *she-meforash b'shas Yerushalmi*, quite interesting, obviously he didn't
have the גמרא Gemara ירושלמי *Gemara Yerushalmi*, it's I heard somebody quoting
רב האי *Rav Hai* saying it's a ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* that says ופקודת
אלעזר בן אהרן הכהן Aharon HaKohen שמן המאור וקטורת הסמים ומנחת התמיד
ושמן המשחה *u'fkudat Elazar ben Aharon ha-Kohen shemen ha-ma'or u'ktoret ha-samim u'minhat
ha-tamid v'shemen ha-mishha*, like that's the פסוק *pasuk* about what אלעזר הכהן
*Elazar ha-Kohen* carried. So we have two שמנים *shemanim*, שמן המאור *shemen
ha-ma'or* ושמן המשחה *v'shemen ha-mishha*. So שמן, אחד בימינו ואחד בשמאלו *shemen,
ehad b'yimino v'ehad b'smolo*. So one flask of oil in his right
hand, one in his left hand. וקטורת בחיקו *u'ktoret b'heiko*, and the
incense in your chest, again I don't know what exactly what that
means, obviously in some maybe pocket or something. וחביתין בכתף *v'havitin ba-kateif*,
and the, you know, and the מנחות *menahot* would be on the
shoulder. Again why exactly a מנחה *minhah* on a shoulder? Doesn't seem
like it's so heavy. Anyway, but the point being that here's a
פסוק *pasuk* that lists many things that he was responsible for and
the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* reads it not just he's responsible for but
he carried. How do you carry seven different things? Well, you've got
to put them on different parts of your body. Okay, so anyway,
somehow we understand that that's how they carried and therefore you are
חייב Chayav *hayav*. Now, what's important to note is the following about
this and, you know, is that until we get to the next
part of the משנה Mishna *Mishnah*, you know let me read the
משנה Mishna *Mishnah* and then I'll tell you sort of how we
can go back and think about the first half of the משנה
Mishna *Mishnah*. כלאחר ידו Kil-ahar yado. *k'l'ahar yado*, if it's by the
back of his hand, וברגלו *u'v'raglo*, if it's on his leg, בפיו
*b'piv*, in his mouth, ובמפרקו *u'v'mafreko*, Rashi says מפרקו *mafreko* means the
underarm, תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says מפרקו *mafreko* means the elbow. Actually it's
very interesting, if you look at תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* to מפרקו *mafreko*,
it says והוא שקורין קודא *v'hu she-korin kuda* ולא כמו שפירש בקונטרס
אישלש *v'lo k'mo she-peireish bakontreis ishlash*. So what's קודא *kuda* and אישלש
*ishlash*? So I don't know if you have this, if you look
at the far right, at the very far right margin, even right
of Rashi, there's a little א *alef*, it says קודא, בלשון אשכנז
*kuda, bi'lshon Ashkenaz* אלבויגן *elbogen*.
So
all right, and then אישלש *ishlash* is אקסלן *axlen*. I don't know
how אקסלן *axlen* is, but then anyway that's the underarm. Okay, so
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* makes the very strong argument that מפרק *mafrek* is
the elbow. So you carried in your, on your leg, in your
mouth, in your elbow, באזנו *b'ozno*, you somehow in his ear, בשערו
*bi's'aro*, in his hair, ובפונדתו *u'v'fundato*, in his belt, ופיה למטה *u'fih
l'mata*, now if this belt basically the mouth, you know presumably it
was some type of like a hollow belt so you could like
put something on the inside of it, but if the opening was
facing down then obviously it's not a good way to store things,
they fall out. So all those things you're, בין פונדתו לחלוקו *bein
fundato l'haluko*, between your belt and your garment, that would seem like
a pretty good place to store something, right? Certain things you could
store very nicely between your belt and your garment, etc. So I
don't know. ובשפת חלוקו *u'vi'sfat haluko*, or at the at the edge
of your garment, at the hem, במנעלו *bi'mnalo*, in your shoe, בסנדלו
*bi'sandalo*, or your sandal. Again sometimes people, right, they want to hide
things like their wallet or their money or their... you know where
you doing it?
If you're in like a dangerous place, that's a normal way of
doing it.
I know, so that doesn't, does it get defined by place? We'll
discuss some of that stuff. Like putting in your bra. Right, okay.
פטור Patur. *patur*, you're exempt, שלא הוציא כדרך המוציאין Kederech Hamotzi'in. *she-lo
hotzi k'derech ha-motzi'in*, you did not carry the way that normal people
carry out. Now this seems to be or what it is is
it's beginning to lay the foundation, which we'll see in the next
משנה Mishna, *Mishnah*, of a principle called שינוי Shinuy *shinui*, doing something
in an unusual way. And the other phrase for שינוי Shinuy *shinui*
is, anybody know? כלאחר יד k'l'achar yad. *k'l'ahar yad*. You will notice
that that was the first example, כלאחר ידו k'l'achar yado, *k'l'ahar yado*.
Now actually כ *k'* means like, לאחר ידו Le-ahar yado. *l'ahar yado*
the back of his hand. If you look at
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*, לאחר ידו *l'ahar yado*, תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says ולספרים
דגרסי כלאחר ידו *u'l'sfarin d'garsi k'l'ahar yado*, יש אומרים דברגלו הוי פירש
כלאחר ידו *yeish omrim d'v'raglo ha-vei peireish k'l'ahar yado*. כלאחר ידו *k'l'ahar
yado* is a... meaning before you make it like a generic and
we're talking about something concrete. First we talk about the reality of
carrying it something on the back of your hand, לאחר ידו. Then
what we can do is we can say this whole category of
unusual is כלאחר ידו. It's like the back of the hand, which
is the first example of what it means to do it in
an unusual way. Okay, so the simple way of reading this whole
משנה, mishnah which clearly is ענף Anaf to this משנה, mishnah is
if you do things in the normal way you're חייב Chayav and
the abnormal way you're פטור. Patur. That's the principle of שינוי Shinuy?
or לאחר ידו. However what?
In an off-hand way.
In an off-hand way. All right,
right, so
exactly. Now, but the one thing to remember though about this is
specifically when you are talking about carrying, if we didn't have some
later משניות Mishnayot which we're about to see that apply a similar
principle to other מלאכות, Melachos we could have said that this was
unique to carrying, because you might remember how much by carrying we
needed to sort of prove every separate aspect of carrying. You're חייב
chayav when you go from רשות היחיד Reshut Hayachid to רשות הרבים,
Reshut Harabim, from רשות הרבים Reshut Harabim to רשות היחיד, Reshut Hayachid,
you're חייב chayav if you do it this way, if you do
it that way, every single one we had a proof from the
משכן. Mishkan And תוספות Tosafos makes the point which I've said to
you multiple times that it's because this is not a מלאכה Melacha
like the other ones that really produces something. When you produce something
we don't hyper-focus on the exact process, right? Cooking, it could be
cooking, it could be baking, it could be frying, all those things
you don't have to prove that they were in the משכן. Mishkan.
They basically are similar type of a thing of producing something. Carrying,
which isn't producing, focuses on the process. So if it's the process,
every process might be distinct from every other one and therefore you
have to prove that every individual process is part of what that
מלאכה Melacha is. If that's true, this idea of the beginning of
the משנה mishnah saying well this is the way בני קהת Bnei
Kehat did it, but this way is not כדרך המוציאין. Kederech Hamotzi'in
So כדרך המוציאין maybe broadens it just from בני קהת, Bnei Kehat
but the point is you could have read this משנה Mishnah to
be specifically about carrying. We look very specifically at בני קהת, how
was it done in the משכן Mishkan as opposed to other ways
because it's all focused on the process and all very much exactly
the way it's done in the משכן. Mishkan? So that is I
think the first emphasis of this משנה Mishnah or one aspect. Of
course what then happens is that this becomes broader as well. This
is a principle that doesn't remain by just carrying which is hyper-focused
on the process, it becomes general process by שבת Shabbat about this
idea of שינוי Shinuy doing things in an unusual way that you
are פטור. ptor And the question does become how do you define
שינוי? Shinuy Let's say some of these issues, for example under certain
circumstances would be the normal way of doing it. Would you be
חייב chayav, when those are the circumstances? That becomes a critical question
and it's very important להלכה L'halacha because very often there are things
on שבת Shabbat? that warrant violating דרבנן Derabbanan but not violating דאורייתא.
De'oraisa. Or sometimes if it's a double דרבנן, Derabbanan, like it's a
דרבנן Derabbanan of a דרבנן Derabbanan or something. And therefore שינוי Shinuy?
is always the easiest thing to get to. Okay, do it with
the back of your hand, do it with your left hand not
your right hand, do it this way, do it with your elbow,
do it something. And the question always becomes how much of a
שינוי Shinuy and under what circumstances do you define this as a
שינוי? Shinuy And that is something that is a critical issue. The
גמרא Gemara touches on it to some degree we will see, but
a critical issue in הלכה. Halacha. I'll just point out one final
aspect about שינוי Shinuy that is somewhat clear from this משנה, Mishnah.
which is
does שינוי Shinuy? have to affect
the end result? Right here it doesn't affect the end result. Whether
I carry it in my elbow or in my belt or in
my hand, the object getting to the place it's getting to got
there just as well and the end result is just as good.
If I turn on the light switch with my elbow, the lights
are going to burn just as easily. So שינוי Shinuy does not
have to affect the end result. Does it have to make it
more harder for me to do? What if it's just as easy
even though it's unusual? Let's say it's relatively easy for me to
flip on a light switch
with my elbow or whatever. Okay maybe is that a שינוי? Shinuy
Does it have to be harder to do like use my foot
right? Or use my mouth to turn on the light switch? Again
these are questions about how much unusual that is. And it does
seem from a number of cases that things could be considered a
שינוי Shinuy even if they don't affect the end result, even if
they're not harder to do, just because it's an unusual way of
doing it. One final point about the general question of שינוי shinuy
and then we'll read the גמרא Gemara which is does שינוי shinuy
apply by things outside of שבת? Shabbos For example, the אגלי טל
Eglei Tal who wrote a famous book on הלכות שבת Hilchos Shabbat
where his point was he was going to write on the למד
טית מלאכות, Lamed Tet Melachos, so he called it טל Tal because
טל Tal is למד טית Lamed Tet reverse. Anyway he only got
through the מלאכות melachos of the first eleven of cooking and of
baking but anyway
but he discusses this issue about there's a discussion in also discussed
earlier. It has to be דרך כתיבה derech ketivah and maybe if
you write it with a wrong hand maybe it's no good. So
they say no, no, no, שינוי shinuy is only an issue for
שבת Shabbos. because of מלאכת מחשבת. melechet machshevet. מלאכת מחשבת melechet machshevet
puts very high criteria and it has to be done in a
very
precise type of way. It doesn't apply by other things. But then
he goes on to show that it's not true, that there's other
הלכות halachos where if you do things in a שינוי shinuy you're
exempt. If you eat something, forbidden food, לאו דרך אכילה, lav derech
achilah, not the normal way of eating, you are exempt. So his
basic point is that there are some types of שינוי shinuy which
are across the board and apply in all cases and there are
other types of שינוי shinuy not only by שבת. Shabbos There are
other types of שינוי shinuy that are so trivial that they only
are a שבת Shabbos. exemption and they're not an exemption in other
areas of הלכה. halacha. Okay, so I'm not going to now try
to describe to you how he divides that line because it's a
little I think it's a little fuzzy when he tries to exactly
define the difference between those two categories. But the point is that
number one, שינוי shinuy in this משנה Mishnah: is about carrying. You
could have emphasized carrying because of the focus on process. We will
see though by the end of the משנה Mishnah. where it talks
about the way people carry and we'll see in later משניות mishnayos
שינוי shinuy becomes extended to other מלאכות as well and it is
worth you know noting that שינוי shinuy also does apply sometimes in
areas even outside of שבת. Shabbat So there's an aspect of שינוי
shinui. which says it's not a normal way of doing it, it's
not the normal act, that can apply everywhere and maybe there's an
aspect of it that is only specific an exemption to הלכות שבת.
hilchos Shabbos. Okay, let's take a look now at the גמרא. Gemara
אמר רבי אלעזר Amar Rabbi Elazar המוציא משא למעלה מעשרה טפחים Hamotzi
masa lemala mi-asarah tefachim
חייב שכן משא בני קהת. chayav sheken masa Bnei Kehat. So here,
emphasizing like I think the first point of the משנה mishna that
we look to the משכן Mishkan. to define what the מלאכה melachah
is. So he says forget the שינוי shinui discussion. What what did
they do in the משכן? Mishkan So he says well if you
carry something above עשרה טפחים asarah tefachim you're חייב chayav. because that
is the way the בני קהת carried. Now what does that mean?
It means remember we've taught for a long time that the רשות
הרבים, reshus harabim, the airspace of the רשות הרבים reshus harabim only
goes up till עשרה טפחים, asarah tefachim, right about three feet. Okay
so if I went ahead and I carried something in a רשות
הרבים reshus harabim and let's say I put it against a wall,
you know, or I put it on a ledge higher than עשרה
טפחים, asarah tefachim, I'd be exempt because it never was in the
airspace of the רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. Okay let's say however I
went ahead and I carried something over עשרה טפחים asarah tefachim and
then at the end of the at the end of my ד'
אמות arba amos or the end of going from private to public
I put it down. Okay but the basic transporting of it was
not transported, it wasn't think about even the ד' אמות ברשות הרבים
arba amos bereshus harabim it's a better example because there it's not
going transitioning from one to the other, it's actually moving ד' אמות
ברשות הרבים. arba amos bereshus harabim. Well let's say that moving of
the ד' אמות arba amos was over the airspace? Maybe I should
be exempt, I didn't actually move it in רשות הרבים, reshus harabim,
I picked it up, I moved it over the airspace and I
put it down. So he says okay, I understand why you would
think you'd be exempt, you didn't move it in רשות הרבים, reshus
harabim, but we know you're חייב chayav because that's what they did
in the משכן. Mishkan. So again looking to the משכן Mishkan, as
defining exactly the circumstances of חיוב chiyuv and פטור patur. and even
though here there would be a logic to say you'd be exempt.
Now we're going to show where you see that that is true
in the משכן. Mishkan ומשא בני קהת מנלן? U-masa Bnei Kehat minalan?
How do you know that when they carried it in the you
know of בני קהת they carried it above עשרה טפחים? asarah tefachim?
דכתיב De-chsiv the verse says על המשכן ועל המזבח סביב. Al ha-mishkan
ve-al ha-mizbeiach saviv. So it says by the by the the curtains
that were around the חצר chatzer of the משכן, Mishkan. it says
that they that they sort of that they you know that they're
around, they're against the משכן Mishkan and the מזבח, mizbeiach, right the
open air altar, the the מזבח הנחושת. mizbeiach ha-nechoshes. So מקיש מזבח
למשכן Makish mizbeiach le-mishkan it links the מזבח mizbeiach to the altar
to the משכן. Mishkan מה משכן עשר אמות אף מזבח עשר אמות.
Mah mishkan eser amos af mizbeiach eser amos. The same way the
משכן Mishkan, was עשר אמות eser amos high, the altar was עשר
אמות eser amos high. Although the תורה Torah says that the altar
was שלוש אמות shalosh amos high, there's actually a debate of תנאים
Tannaim and some say it doesn't mean שלוש אמות, shalosh amos, it
means that it was שלוש אמות shalosh amos from the sort of
from this ledge that went around it and actually the whole altar
was עשר אמות eser amos high. We'll see why this is going
to be important in a minute. ומשכן גופיה מנלן? U-mishkan gufeih minalan?
And how do you know the משכן Mishkan. was עשר אמות? eser
amos? Okay that's not a challenge, that's a פסוק. דכתיב עשר אמות
אורך הקרש. De-chsiv eser amos orech ha-keresh. Okay וכתיב ויפרוש את האוהל
על המשכן. Ve-chsiv vayifros es ha-ohel al ha-mishkan. Now so we know
that the משכן, Mishkan. the מזבח mizbeiach was עשר אמות eser amos
by link to the משכן. Mishkan, Now let's look at another point.
It says that משה Moshe spread over the awning, you know, the
אהל, ohel, meaning the actual cover, the the curtain cover on top
of the משכן. Mishkan ואמר רב משה רבינו פירסו. Ve-amar Rav Moshe
Rabbeinu pirso. When it says ויפרוש vayifros it doesn't just mean like
he saw that it would get done, but it
means he personally did it, he spread it out. Okay and it
actually means so one guy spreading out the whole cover on the
משכן, Mishkan how do you do that? מכאן אתה למד גובהן של
לויים. Mikan atah lamed govhan shel Leviyim. From here you can see
that the height of the לויים, Leviyim, not just משה, Moshe, of
all the לויים Leviyim were עשר אמות. eser amos. How do you,
how can you spread something over something unless as your height as
the thing it is or even taller than the thing it is?
So if משה Moshe did the whole curtain, you know, you could
say well maybe he was standing on a ladder. Okay? But then
if you got other people to help you maybe, they're standing on
a ladder. But if you're going to do it all by yourself,
right, so you need to be very big or whatever. Anyway, that's
what the גמרא Gemara understands, that משה Moshe was עשר אמות. eser
amot.
I don't know what to tell you. I understand. I don't know
where what's motivating this interpretation. I will say it's also interesting that
then they don't limit it to משה, Moshe, they extend it to
all the לויים. Leviyim. But that could also be because if משה
Moshe was עשר אמות eser amot and they weren't, he would maybe
be like a בעל מום, baal mum, you know, that he would
be so unusual. So you have to, that's a general trait of
all the לויים, Leviyim, you know. Right.
And it avoids going then somebody it wasn't necessarily משה Moshe who
took it apart and put it on and off.
Oh right, you had to do it all the time, so maybe
you wouldn't have to get משה Moshe to do it if all
of them were עשר אמות. eser amot.
It makes even more sense that אהרן הכהן could lift them up
and wave them all.
Well, he was also לוי Levi so he was as big as
they were. Alright, so anyway, so משה Moshe and all the לויים
Leviyim are fifteen feet tall. Okay, so now what does that do
for us? וגמירי, U'gemiri, and we have a tradition, דכל טונא דמדלי
במוטות, dekhol tuna demidlei be-motot, any type of a burden that's carried
on a
pole, תילתא מלעיל ותרי תילתא מלרע, tilta mil'eil u-trei tiltei milra, that
the effective way presumably of carrying it was a third above the
pole and two thirds below. Right, so you're carrying something on a
pole or you know like they would carry like the grapes or
you know that the picture that famous picture they'd carry the ארון
Aron. whatever they'd carry, a third would be above the pole, two
thirds below. אשתכח דהוי מדלי טובא. Ishtakach de-havi midlei tuva. So let's
figure it out. They were carrying the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. The מזבח Mizbe'ach
was עשר אמות, eser amot, we just said. They're עשר אמות. eser
amot. So when they're carrying the מזבח, Mizbe'ach, a third of the
מזבח Mizbe'ach is above the pole, two thirds is below the pole.
So two thirds of עשר אמות eser amot is what, six and
a third, six and, right, six and a third. Is that right?
Six and two thirds. Six and two thirds אמות amot below the
pole. So what's the space from the bottom of the מזבח Mizbe'ach
till the ground if they are עשר אמות? eser amot? So I
mean well it depends, are they עשר אמות eser amot to their
shoulders or עשר אמות eser amot to their head? Let's say they're
תשע אמות tesha amot to their shoulders. Let's even say they're שמונה
אמות shmoneh amot to their shoulders. It doesn't matter. Now you have,
well it does, so anyway, but let's say okay, let's say they're
תשע אמות. tesha amot. So you have let's say שתי אמות shtei
amot from the bottom of the מזבח Mizbe'ach to the ground. So
obviously the bottom of the מזבח Mizbe'ach was carried over עשרה טפחים
asarah tefachim over the
ground. It was higher than עשרה טפחים asarah tefachim off of the
ground. So that's one proof that, well it makes a lot of
assumptions, that the מזבח Mizbe'ach was עשר, eser, they were עשר, eser,
a third above, two thirds below, but if you put all that
together the bottom of the מזבח Mizbe'ach was more than עשרה טפחים
asarah tefachim off the ground.
But if you compare it to our times, none of us are
עשר אמות eser amot tall but we're learning from them, which was
a one time...
what can I tell you? That's right, maybe it should be proportional.
Okay, I don't know. ואיבעית אימא, V'iba'it eima, but again the עשרה
טפחים asarah tefachim is the height of רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim, so
that's true for all people. ואיבעית אימא V'iba'it eima if you want,
I'll give you a better way of saying it. מארון, Me-Aron, we
can learn it out from the ארון. Aron This is a little
easier. דאמר מר, De-amar mar, we taught, ארון תשעה, Aron tishah, וכפורת
טפח. ve-kaporet tefach. The ארון Aron was nine טפחים, tefachim, that's in
the תורה, Torah, okay, it says you know אמה וחצי amah v'chetzi
which is nine טפחים, tefachim, and the כפורת kaporet which was put
on the ארון Aron is a טפח. tefach. הרי כאן עשרה. Harei
kan asarah. That makes the whole height of the ארון Aron ten
טפחים. tefachim. וגמירי, V'gemiri, but we're still going to introduce our assumption
of carrying, דכל טונא דמדלי במוטות, dekhol tuna demidlei be-motot, anything carried
on a beam on a whatever pole, תילתא מלעיל ותרי תילתא מלרע,
tilta mil'eil u-trei tiltei milra, one third above and two thirds below,
one third above, two thirds below. אשתכח דלמעלה מעשרה הוי קאי. Ishtakach
de-l'maala me-asarah havi kai. So we see that if two thirds of
עשרה טפחים asarah tefachim were below, you know whatever six and two
thirds טפחים tefachim were below. Now how high is the normal person
from the feet to his shoulder? So that another גמרא Gemara says
would be three אמות, amot, שמונה עשרה טפחים, shmoneh esreh tefachim, which
means if a טפח tefach is about you know about three and
a half inches that's fifty-four, sixty-three inches, which is what, a little
more than five feet, which actually okay so that's probably for Jews
that's probably average. So anyway, so you have שמונה עשרה טפחים shmoneh
esreh tefachim from the ground to my shoulder, you have two thirds
of the ארון Aron. below my shoulder, which is six and two
thirds, so there's about eleven and change טפחים tefachim from the ground
to the bottom of the ארון. Aron So the ארון Aron? was
carried more than עשרה טפחים asarah tefachim off of the ground. That's
a much easier way of doing it. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says, but the גמרא Gemara says וליגמר ממשה, ve-ligmar me-Moshe,
why do you have to go to the ארון? How about that
previous one learning it out from משה, Moshe, that was nice? So
the גמרא Gemara says no, דילמא משה שאני, dilma Moshe shani, maybe
משה Moshe was it was only משה Moshe that was עשר אמות.
eser amot. Maybe it wasn't the rest of לויים Leviyim so you
can't learn out from that. Okay, דאמר מר de-amar mar because we
said, אין השכינה שורה אלא על חכם גיבור ועשיר ובעל קומה. Ein
HaShekhinah shoreh ella al chakham, gibbor, ve-ashir, u-vaal komah.
The divine presence only rests on somebody who is wise, you know,
mighty, rich, and a person of stature, here reading stature in a
very literal sense. So no, so therefore if we know that משה
Moshe was עשר אמות, eser amot, it doesn't prove that the other
לויים Leviyim were עשר אמות. eser amot. It makes sense that משה
Moshe was this way. Only לויים Leviyim maybe not that much, but
they at least were ten. Okay. אמר רב, Amar Rav, what? Fifty?
This idea of the bias of society towards tall people, you see,
goes back way, way back. Okay. אמר מר, Amar Mar, אמר מר
משמיה רבי חייא. Amar Mar mishmei Rabbi Chiya. Okay. So that was
the end about how we know higher than ten טפחים. tefachim. Now,
now we're going to move effectively to the second part of the
משנה Mishnah. and this idea of שינוי. shinui So let's take a
look. אמר מר משמיה רבי חייא: Amar Mar mishmei Rabbi Chiya: המוציא
משוי בשבת על ראשו חייב חטאת. Hamotzi masoi b'Shabbat al rosho chayav
chatat. If you carry something on your head, you're חייב, chayav, שכן
אנשי הוצל עושין כן. sheken anshei Hutzal osin ken. The people of
הוצל Hutzal do that way. You know, it's like the women that
carry the baskets on their head or whatever. So in some societies
they carry on their head and therefore you're חייב. chayav. So here
you're taking what's a way of carrying in one society and applying
it across the board. The גמרא Gemara objects. The גמרא Gemara says:
ואנשי הוצל רובא דעלמא? V'anshei Hutzal ruba d'alma? I don't get it.
The people of הוצל Hutzal are the majority of the world we
should define everywhere based on הוצל Hutzal that that constitutes normal? אלא
אי איתמר הכי איתמר. Ela i itmar hachi itmar. If it was
taught, here's how it was taught. אמר רב משמיה רבי חייא: Amar
Rav mishmei Rabbi Chiya: אחד מבני הוצל שהוציא משוי על ראשו בשבת
חייב. Echad mibnei Hutzal shehotzi masoi al rosho b'Shabbas chayav.
If you're in הוצל Hutzal and you carry it on your head,
you're חייב chayav because there, in that location, that's the norm. Okay,
so it could change from location to location. שכן בני עירו עושין
כן. Sheken bnei iro osin ken.
That's what's done in your city. So the גמרא Gemara, says: ותבטל
דעתו אצל כל אדם. Utbatel da'ato etzel kol adam. Now this is
quite interesting. Even in that location, maybe that should not be considered
the norm because it's not the universal norm. Okay? So not only
do we not take a location and apply it universally, we don't
even give it legitimacy, recognize it in its own location. We go
by a universal norm. Okay, how many things are there that are
universal norms? אלא אי איתמר. Ela i itmar. And the גמרא Gemara
just accepts it, doesn't push back. אלא אי איתמר הכי איתמר. Ela
i itmar hachi itmar. Fine. Here's how it said. What completely reversed
what we originally said. המוציא משוי על ראשו פטור. Hamotzi masoi al
rosho patur. If you carry it on your head, you're פטור. Patur,
ואם תמצא לומר אנשי הוצל עושין כן. V'im timtza lomar anshei Hutzal
osin ken. How about the people of הוצל Hutzal and presumably at
least in הוצל Hutzal this should be normal? בטלה דעתו אצל כל
אדם. Batlah da'ato etzel kol adam. No, it doesn't matter. They're not
the, you know, you go by the universal and what they say
doesn't matter. Now תוספות raises the issue because there are other גמרות
Gemaras that seem to say otherwise, that seem to say when we're
defining what are norms, we might not go like if your little
village has some practice, but we would go by like a large
geographic region. And if there's a norm within a large geographic region,
then that would define the norm for the people of that region.
And תוספות tries to figure out when do we look at the
local norms, when do we insist that we sort of... that's not
meaningful, we look at universal norms. Again, although this might seem a
little counterintuitive what this גמרא Gemara says, besides the fact that תוספות
wants to limit it and say there are times we do, the
point still being is that this allows for greater exemption, right? It
means that more things are considered a שינוי shinui if we have
to be looking at things that are, you know, by and large
universal norms. Charlie?
I was just going to ask about application to other areas.
Yeah, so again, the question does go and that's תוספות's issue. Maybe
if it's a large enough geographic area, we would look within that
area as what the norms are. Yes?
The statement about how the שכינה Shechinah rests on... Yeah.
...is
a little disturbing because they're all external qualities. Right. עשיר, Ashir, right.
חכם, Chakham, גבור, Gibbor, nothing about wise or virtuous...
חכם Chakham is wise, virtuous... That's... Right, I mean,
the way I've always understood that, although, you know, is that meaning
in addition to the obvious, meaning in addition to all the, you
know, the clearly sort of substantive criteria, there's these other sort of
more external ones.
The שכינה Shechinah is measuring people and...
Right, it does raise... You're right, you're right to raise that because
it goes exactly to... Even if you read it that way, there
are additional criteria, not the fundamental ones. Right, it goes to the
basic problem of the whole of the second half of שמות Shemot
and all of the stuff about the appearance of the משכן and
about the מומים mumim of the כהנים Kohanim and all of the
aesthetics, which become a part and parcel of what people expect for
something that's holy or divine or important. But, you know, the question
is: why is the תורה Torah sort of, you know, condoning or
reinforcing it rather than, you know, working against it? So that raises
very important questions, you know. And I think you're right about to
what degree do you sort of, you know, try to get to
the people where they're at, you know. האיש יראה לעינים והשם יראה
ללבב. Ha'ish yireh la'einayim v'Hashem yireh lalvav. You know, so we, you
know, if people... it won't resonate with people, then it's going to
be counterproductive. To what degree do you try to move them away
to something more meaningful and substantive? You know, and it does... but
it does raise very significant issues. I think you're absolutely correct. A
lot of those issues are around the משכן and around the כהנים,
Kohanim, so that's a very good point. All right. Yes? One thing
about the... something...
I mean, why would we have thought it wouldn't... why would we
point it out? I mean, our משנה Mishnah. is specifically exemptions and
the head wasn't there.
No, because the question... no, but that's the question, you know. Is
it talking about everywhere? Are there, you know, maybe it depends. I
think it's very clear... it's very much clarifying the scope of the
משנה. Okay. So now, now
we've introduced a couple... a key concept about שינוי shinui? which we
will revisit. it in another day or two. Let's look now at
yet going on other important points about the act of carrying. The
next משנה: המכוין להוציא לפניו ובא לו לאחריו. Hamiskavein lehotzi lefanav uva
lo leacharav.
Here you're carrying in a way that's maybe normal, but it's not
what you were trying to do. You had it attached to your
belt or something, I don't know, around your on a necklace around
your neck, you were you carried your you're carrying your money bag,
I mean not a necklace, that would be an ornament, and accidentally
it slipped behind you. And now it was the you know the
let's say the money like the little money pouch was now was
now behind you and not in front of you. Okay, פטור, patur.
you're exempt because it wasn't what you were trying to do even
though it was maybe a normal way. לאחריו ובא לו לפניו, Leacharav
uva lo lefanav, if you were trying to have it behind you
and it flipped in front of you, חייב, chayav, you're חייב. chayav
What's the difference? We'll see in the גמרא, Gemara the גמרא Gemara
will basically say because when it's in front of you, you can
watch it and guard it better. So it might be not exactly
what you were intending, but it was better than what you were
trying to do. And therefore that's not enough to get you off.
But if it wasn't exactly what you did and it was worse
than what you were trying to do, then that's enough to exempt
you. באמת אמרו, Be’emes amru,
in truth they said, האישה החוגרת בסינר, ha’ishah hachogeret besinar, if a
woman is wearing an apron, בין לפניו בין לאחריו, bein lefanav bein
leacharav, חייב chayav. חייבת, chayaves,
presumably there's something in the apron that's being carried, whether it's in
front of her or behind her, she's she'd be חייב, chayav, it
doesn't matter if it flipped in front or back, שכן ראוי להיות
חוזר shekein raui lihayos chozer because that's normally what happens, the apron
you know naturally sort of you know moves from front to back
and therefore even if you were intending to carry it in the
front, you knew that there was a good chance that it would
move behind, so it's not like we can say your intent was
so rigid and so specific once it was the norm for things
to move. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says, אף מקבלי פתקים, af mekabblei petakim,
even true of people that accept like receipts, so I'll read you
the way תוספות reads it is certain people that would accept various
like receipt for the case, they would also put them in types
of belts in front of them, but the belts would often you
know reverse to the back. So even though there if it does
reverse and it's different than you were intending, since that was the
norm of what would happen, you can't really say that it was
what something you didn't intend. Okay, and again here we are generally
familiar, again, it's important to note what a חידוש chiddush this is,
we're generally familiar with the idea of אינו מתכוין, eino miskavein, but
אינו מתכוין eino miskavein is I was trying to drag the chair
across you know across the backyard and it unintentionally made a furrow.
Here I was trying to take this object out into the street
and I took it out into the street and I took it
exactly where I wanted to take it, like there's another אינו מתכוין,
eino miskavein, I tried to throw it four אמות amos and it
rolled and it went eight אמות. amos. Okay, but there at least
something was different in the result. Here I tried to take it
out, I took it out, I put it down where I wanted
to put it down. The only difference is that in the process
some way the process was being done was not exactly the way
I was trying to do it. Okay, and that again is an
interesting question, how much would you apply this to things outside of
carrying? You know, let's say, I don't know, I was trying to
turn on the front burner of my stove and I accidentally turned
on the back burner. It happens sometimes you get your thing on
the wrong on the wrong hand, right? So you'd say, okay, you're
not חייב chayav, for making a fire, you know, because you because
you were trying to do it on the front I mean it's
not my hand slipped, right? I knew where my hand was, I
thought though I was going to turn on the front I mean
what degree would you say if the process was a little different
even if it didn't affect the result, is that enough to exempt
you? So that's really a חידוש, chiddush, a major חידוש, chiddush, and
at least here we're saying it by carrying, how broadly to extend
that is an interesting question. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara.
says. מאי שנא לפניו ובא לו לאחריו, Mai shna lefanav uva lo
leacharav, why what difference does it make the first case, when it
started in front of you and reversed to behind you, דפטור, depatur,
you're exempt, דלא איתעביד מחשבתו, delo isavid machshavto, wasn't exactly what you
were trying to
do. לאחריו ובא לו לפניו, Leacharav uva lo lefanav, נמי לא איתעביד
מחשבתו nami lo isavid machshavto also what you're you know it didn't
happen the way you were trying to make it happen. So אמר
רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elezar, תברה, tavra, break it in half. מי
ששנה זו לא שנה זו, Mi sheshana zu lo shana zu, which
is a pretty amazing read of the משנה. You're right, they're two
different lines from two different sources, one source said when it things
change you're exempt, the other said when things change you're חייב. chayav,
And it really you know two totally different opinions slapped together, which
is a pretty shocking read. So אמר רבא Amar Rava ומאי קושיא,
u’mai koshya, רבא Rava said I don't even understand the problem, it's
obvious what the difference is. דילמא לפניו ובא לו לאחריו, Dilma lefanav
uva lo leacharav, if it starts in front of you and goes
to the back, היינו טעמא דפטור, hainu taama depatur, here's why you're
exempt, דנתכוון לשמירה מעולה ועלתה בידו שמירה פחותה. deniskavein lishmirah me’ulah ve’alsah
beyado shmirah pechusa. You were trying to do it in a way
that it was well protected, and when you carried it in a
way that it was you did it in a way that it
was poorly
protected. ואחריו ובא לו לפניו, Ve’acharay uva lo lefanav, and the case
where it started behind you and you it wound up moving in
front of you, היינו טעמא דחייב, hainu taama dechayav, here's why you're
חייב, chayav דנתכוון לשמירה פחותה deniskavein lishmirah pechusa you were going to
carry it in a way where it was poorly
protected, ועלתה בידו שמירה מעולה. ve’alsah beyado shmirah me’ulah. So it was
not exactly what you were planning, but again, it wasn't it was
actually better and therefore that's not enough to get you off the
hook. אלא מאי קושיא, Ella mai koshya, so okay you know רבא
Rava what you're saying רבא Rava is so obvious, it's so funny.
So now what you're answer was such a good answer, what was
even bothering us in the first place? So מאי קושיא, mai kushya,
so דיוקא דמתניתין קשיא, diyuka d'matnitin kashya, we were bothered by the
inference of the Mishnah. What does the Mishnah say? המתכוין להוציא לפניו
ובא לו לאחריו פטור. hamitkavein l'hotzi l'fanav u'va lo l'achraiv patur. If
you tried to do it in front and it went to the
back, you're exempt. הא לאחריו ובא לו לאחריו חייב. ha l'achraiv u'va
lo l'achraiv chayav. So if you just wanted to do it behind
you and you actually succeeded, you'd be חייב, chayav obviously. It seems
obvious, right? The only problem here was that it was what you
weren't intending. אימא סיפא, eima seifa, let's look at the end of
the
Mishnah. לאחריו ובא לו לפניו חייב. l'achraiv u'va lo l'fanav chayav. So
הוא דחייב, hu d'chayav, that's why you're חייב, chayav, because in the
end not just you're even חייב chayav. even though it wasn't what
you were intending. To read the Mishnah that you're only חייב chayav.
in that case because it was in front of you, הא לאחריו
ובא לו לאחריו פטור, ha l'achraiv u'va lo l'achraiv patur, if it
stayed behind you, you'd be exempt. Which is again a very forced
read to get a problem, right? You know, so to read it
as though, so you know, the first part of the Mishnah assumes
that behind you is a חייב, chayav. you started that way, and
the second one reading the Mishnah to say that only because it's
in front of you are you חייב. chayav. If it remains behind
you, you're exempt. So אמר רבי אלעזר, amar Rabbi Elazar, so the
גמרא Gemara says
אמר רבי אלעזר, amar Rabbi Elazar, תברא מי ששנה זו לא שנה
זו. tavra mi sheshana zu lo shana zu. So that's where רבי
אלעזר Rabbi Elazar said fine, there are different opinions slapped together. אמר
רב אשי, amar Rav Ashi, so רב אשי Rav Ashi said I
still don't get the problem. ומה קושיא, u'mai kushya, why is it
difficult? דילמא לא מיבעיא קאמר, dilma lo mibaya ka'amar, which is obviously
the right read of the Mishnah. Maybe it goes without saying. לא
מיבעיא לאחריו ובא לו לאחריו דחייב. lo mibaya l'achraiv u'va lo l'achraiv
d'chayav. Of course if you started, if you wanted to take it
behind you and you succeeded in doing that, of course you'd be
חייב. chayav. דעבד מחשבתו, d'avad machshavto, you did what you intended and
that would be normal enough way of
carrying. אלא אפילו לאחריו ובא לו לפניו איצטריכא ליה, ela afilu l'achraiv
u'va lo l'fanav itztricha lei, that's what you have to tell me
that even there you're חייב. chayav. סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka datach amina,
I would have thought הואיל ולא עביד מחשבתו, ho'il v'lo avid machshavto,
since your intent was not done successfully, לא ליחייב, lo l'chayev, not
be חייב. chayav קא משמע לן ka mashma lan דמתכוין לשמירה פחותה
ועלתה בידו שמירה מעולה דחייב, d'mitkavein l'shmira p'chuta v'alta b'yado shmira m'ula
d'chayav, to tell you
that since you tried to do a lower level and it succeeded
in the higher level, even though it's not exactly what you intended,
even in that case you're חייב. chayav? Okay, so in the end
the גמרא Gemara it's quite a fascinating גמרא. Gemara Like the גמרא
Gemara says the Mishnah makes a lot of sense, there's no problem,
but we have a tradition that there was a problem in the
Mishnah to the point that there was an opinion that actually said
the two had, there are two separate sources and they were slapped
together and they're and they're contradictory. And we can't figure out what
the problem of the Mishnah is because the Mishnah makes total sense.
So the גמרא Gemara sort of ends with that and then it
says, but you know what, we're not making this up out of
thin air. ואימא לאחריו ובא לו לאחריו תנאי היא. v'eima l'achraiv u'va
lo l'achraiv tannai hi. Maybe when you carried it behind you and
even when you intended to do that, that's a debate of תנאים
tannaim whether that's considered normal or not. Why? דתניא, d'tanya, who taught
in a ברייתא. braita. המוציא מעות בפונדתו פיה למעלה חייב. hamotzi ma'ot
b'fundato piha l'ma'ala chayav. If you have it in your in your
belt, again it's a hollow belt. So if the opening is facing
up so the stuff won't fall out, then you're חייב. chayav, That
would be a normal way to carry stuff like a money belt
or something. פיה למטה, piha l'mata, if the opening is facing down
of the of the belt, then רבי יהודה מחייב וחכמים פוטרין. Rabbi
Yehuda mechayev v'chachamim potrin. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you're חייב chayav
and the חכמים chachamim say you're exempt. So אמר להם רבי יהודה,
amar lahem Rabbi Yehuda, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said listen, אי אתם
מודים בלאחריו ובא לו לאחריו שהוא חייב? ee atem modim b'l'achraiv u'va
lo l'achraiv she'hu chayav? Don't you agree that if somebody carries something
on their back intentionally you're חייב? chayav. And meaning it doesn't have
to be, you know, what is the range of normal? So you're
saying if the opening is facing down that's not normal. I say,
you know, there's a slightly broader range of normal. Carrying something on
your back is חייב, chayav. so carrying something in the money, in
the belt with the opening facing down is also within the range
of normal. So shouldn't you admit that this is also within the
range of normal? ואמרו לו, v'amru lo, they said back to him,
no. ואי אתם מודה כלאחר ידו ורגלו שהוא פטור? v'ee atem modeh
k'l'achar yado v'raglo she'hu patur? Don't you agree that when it's enough
of a change like it's כלאחר ידו, it's different enough that you're
exempt? So this is different enough when it's behind you. All right.
So so that seems to be the debate. That seems to be
the debate. I'm sorry, not behind you. This is different enough when
the opening of the money belt is facing downwards. So they seem
to be debating whether to put this case of the opening of
the money belt facing downwards in the normal category which has a
range which includes carrying it behind you or in the not normal
category of exempt. So אמר רבי יהודה, amar Rabbi Yehuda, so רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says, אני אמרתי דבר אחד והן אמרו דבר אחד.
ani amarti davar echad v'hen amru davar echad. I made my one
point, they made their point. I wanted to compare it to, you
know, behind you. They wanted to compare it to כלאחר יד. ke'lacher
yad, אני לא מצאתי תשובה לדבריהם. ani lo matzati tshuva l'divreihem. I
don't have a response to their proof. והם לא מצאו תשובה לדברי.
v'hem lo matzu tshuva l'divrai. And they don't have a response to
my proof. Okay, that was a nice summing up. But basically like
okay, we have these two categories: normal with a certain range and
not normal, and we can't figure out which one this this case
of of carrying it with the opening below whether it fits in
category A or category B. Nobody can prove their case. Okay, fine.
Now we're going to analyze this. מכדי קאמר להו אי אתם מודים.
michdee ka'amar lehu ee atem modim. Since he says, look, don't you
admit that this falls into this category of carrying it behind you?
So now if you take a step back and the way sort
of I've been explaining it, it's clear what they're debating. of all
agree on the existence of two categories: normal with a range, the
range is exemplified by carrying it behind you, and not normal, which
is כלאחר יד, ke'lacher yad and the question is this case of
the money belt with the opening below, which is right at the
border, which of those two categories does it fall? But nobody debates
the two categories and everybody agrees that carrying it behind you you're
חייב chayav, even though it's a little bit outside of one hundred
percent normal. Okay, that's the simple read and that's what the גמרא
Gemara is going to say at the end. But at this stage,
the גמרא Gemara is trying to argue that the question of carrying
it behind you is a debate. So what they're going to say
is that actually the reason the rabbis disagree with רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda is because they actually deny that carrying behind you is considered
normal. And their definition of normal is much narrower, doesn't even include
the example of carrying it behind you. So let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara. says like this: מכדי דקאמר להו אי אתם
מודים, Michdi d'ka'amar lehu ee atem modim, since רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says to them, look, don't you guys admit that carrying it behind
you is still normal
enough? לאו מכלל דפליגי עליה, Lav michlal d'paligi alei, presumably no, that's
the rabbis would say no we don't admit to that. Carrying it
behind you is פטור. patur? That's not within the range of normal.
So the גמרא says: ולטעמיך, u'l'ta'ameich, no, that can't be. It can't
be they're arguing what's how those categories are
defined. דקאמר ליה, d'ka'amar lei, when they say to him אי אתה
מודה, ee ata modeh, don't you agree that כלאחר יד ke'lacher yad?
is פטור? patur. Would you say that he disagrees with that? מכלל
דמחייב רבי יהודה, Michlal d'mechayev Rabbi Yehuda, you think רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda would disagree with כלאחר יד? ke'lacher yad והתניא, Ve'hatanya, כלאחר ידו
ורגלו דברי הכל פטור, ke'lacher yado u'raglo divrei hakol patur, that actually
when it's the back of the hand everybody agrees you're פטור. patur.
אלא לאחריו ובא לו לאחריו דברי הכל חייב, Ela l'acharyav u'va lo
l'acharyav divrei hakol chayav,
when you want to carry it behind you everybody agrees you're חייב.
chayav, כלאחר ידו ורגלו דברי הכל פטור, Ke'lacher yado u'raglo divrei hakol
patur, and when it's כלאחר יד ke'lacher yad everybody agrees you're פטור.
patur, כי פליגי, Ki pligi, and the whole debate is which category
to put this case of the belt. בפונדתו ופיה למטה, B'fundato u'fiha
l'mata,
the belt with the opening below. מר מדמי ליה ללאחריו ובא לו
לאחריו, Mar medami lei l'acharyav u'va lo l'acharyav, one says that it's
within the range of normal because normal is not so narrow, it
includes the case of carrying something behind you. ומר מדמי ליה, U'mar
medami lei, and there says yes I agree normal is not so
narrow and includes carrying behind you, but this is even more unusual
than that, מדמי ליה לכלאחר ידו ורגלו, medami lei l'ke'lacher yado u'raglo,
puts it in the כלאחר יד ke'lacher yad category. Okay, so that
was very nice I think in describing this idea. We have a
range of normal and at a certain point it's really not within
the normal way of doing it, and some things can be debated
which of those categories they fall in. But that should not be
interpreted to mean that they're debating whether carrying it behind you is
חייב. chayav. Everybody would agree that is חייב, chayav. that normal is
not defined so narrowly, it includes even cases that are a little
bit outside of the norm. Okay, so that is the upshot of
all of that is that besides this amazing חידוש chiddush of the
משנה that even when everything gets done as the end result is
exactly the way you wanted it, if the process was a little
bit different, a little bit worse, you're פטור, besides that we have
nice also restatement of this idea of שינוי shinui. and כלאחר יד
ke'lacher yad that the idea that there's a range of normal. It's
not one hundred percent everybody the only way of the classic way
of doing it. It includes a certain range. And at a certain
point that's already considered to be כלאחר יד and some things can
be debated which category they fall in. Okay, באמת אמרו האישה, Be'emet
amru ha'isha, now the last point about the apron reversing itself around.
So תנא, tana, and there because since even if you weren't intending
it's like you intended because that's normal. תנא כל באמת הלכה היא,
Tana kol be'emet halacha hi, anytime we say in truth they said
that actually is the way we rule. Also there's an idea that
הלכה halacha doesn't just mean it's the way we rule but הלכה
halacha actually means that it's like a tradition. Some even go so
far as to say it's a הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai.
Okay,
so that's an interesting phrase to unpack. רבי יהודה אומר אף מקבלי
פתקין, Rabbi Yehuda omer af mekablay pitkin, תנא שכן לבלרי מלכות עושים
כן, tana sheken lavlarei malchut osim ken, the same idea of like
the king's scribes that they have various belts with all their stuff
on it and sometimes those belts reverse themselves and move around their
waist and that's a very normal type of a thing.
Okay, so it's just like אנשי הוצל Anshei Hutzal kind of thing.
Right, well yeah, but you do raise an interesting question. Is it
that this type of belt, like here it's women and aprons, so
it does become somewhat circumstantial but maybe it's in all places women
and aprons, in all places, again that raises that important question of
how much do you sort of define it in a particular context
for a particular people, particular thing, right, how do you define what
is what is שינוי? shinuy Okay, so now the גמרא says by
the way the thing about the shoe, again like sometimes it is
like if you go out running or something, you put your ID
in your shoe or something like that. But there were times where
Jews were like if you were outdoors without ID papers on, you
could get into major trouble thrown into prison or whatever, and there
were of course questions about what did they do on שבת Shabbos,
without an עירוב? eiruv? And some said okay, put it in your
shoe or something, put it in your hat, do it with a
type of a שינוי. shinuy, So again, it's always the question about
what types of things justify doing
דרבנן. d'rabbanan.
So putting it in your shoe, like if you're in a dangerous
place, is also considered a שינוי shinuy, even though it's something people
would do on—well there
it wasn't—well there it wasn't
danger—it was dangerous because if you didn't have your papers on. It
wasn't dangerous because of carrying itself, right, but it's a case of
like where people do put things in their shoes because they don't
want to be found with, of course if enough people knew about
that, the shoe wouldn't help. So anyway, alright, moving on. המוציא ככר
לרשות הרבים חייב. Hamotzi kikar lereshus harabim chayav. If you take a
loaf of bread into the רשות הרבים reshus harabim you're חייב, chayav,
that's pretty obvious, but it gets to the second point. הוציאו שנים
פטורין. Hotziu shenayim peturin. If two people carry it, and this is
another great exemption for שבת, is שנים שעשו. shenayim she'asu. Have two
people do it. Okay, and something that could be done by one
person and is done by two, it's an unusual way of doing
it, and therefore
it is exempt. So we've now done שינוי, shinuy. we've done not
having precise כוונה kavana which is not something you can use because
you can't have intent to not have precise anyway, but we've also
done the case of הוציאו שנים שעשו. hotziu shenayim she'asu. Okay.
Even if it's easier to do with two people?
No, let's keep on reading. לא יכול אחד להוציאו והוציאו שנים. Lo
yachol echad lehotzio vehotziu shenayim. If it was not a one-person job
but a two-person job, it was a sofa, in that case שנים
חייבין. shenayim chayavin. Then they are והוציאו שנים vehotziu shenayim then they're
חייבין, chayavin, then they're liable because it was a normal way of
doing it. Yeah. רבי שמעון פוטר. Rabbi Shimon poter. רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon says even in that case you're exempt because a מלאכה melacha
is done by one person, not by two people. So one way
you could frame this is a case of שינוי, shinuy. maybe that's
the first approach, it's more or less an example of שינוי. shinuy
And when it's normal, you're חייב. chayav, But certainly for רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon that's not true, there's a general exemption of two people,
and that might even be true for the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
even if it's not such a שינוי. shinuy, If it's two people
and could be done by one, then it's like it's not all
my מלאכה melacha and therefore I'm off the hook. So like another
example becomes, I don't know, again, the questions about sometimes this is
another standard thing that's used.
I'm trying to remember, I know רב עובדיה יוסף Rav Ovadia Yosef
uses it a lot. I don't know, let's say a case again
about some issue about there's no עירוב eiruv and carrying and this
and that, so you have like two people pushing a baby carriage
or two people holding on to something or something like that. Again,
I'm not פוסק poskening here, every case you have to look at
whether the circumstances warrant, but there could be times when you'd say
two people should do it and it's not a שינוי shinui but
it's enough of a שינוי, but it's an exemption because one person
could do it and two are, and that gets you off the
אליבא דכולי עלמא aliba dechulei alma also, you're exempt. In other words,
if it really is a two-person job and you somehow managed to
do it yourself?
That would be the second half of the משנה. Oh, that could
be. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, ואמרי
לה אמר אביי, ve'amri lah amar Abaye, ואמרי לה במתניתא תנא, ve'amri
lah bemasnisa tanna, some say אביי Abaye says, some say it was
taught in a ברייתא. Braisa. זה יכול וזה יכול. Zeh yachol vezeh
yachol. Now we're sort of abstracting it, getting to the heart of
the משנה. If it's a case where each one could do it
alone and two people do it, רבי מאיר מחייב ורבי יהודה ורבי
שמעון פוטרין. Rabbi Meir mechayav veRabbi Yehuda veRabbi Shimon potrin. רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir doesn't believe in this exemption of done by two people.
If even in the case where each person could do it alone
and it's strange for them to do it together, רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir still says you're חייב. chayav. ורבי יהודה ורבי שמעון veRabbi Yehuda
veRabbi Shimon say you're exempt. זה אינו יכול וזה אינו יכול. Zeh
eino yachol vezeh eino yachol. How about if it really required two
people?
There רבי יהודה ורבי מאיר מחייבים. Rabbi Yehuda veRabbi Meir mechayvim. There
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda goes over to רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir's camp.
רבי Rabbi says if it needed two people, it was a sofa,
then you're חייב, chayav, then it's normal for two people to take
it out. ורבי שמעון veRabbi Shimon as we saw in our משנה
פוטר, Mishnah poter, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says no, two people are
always exempt even if it's a type of thing that required two
people. זה יכול וזה אינו יכול. Zeh yachol vezeh eino yachol. How
about a case where one person was able and the other wasn't?
Like a type of a thing where I don't know, I can
carry it, but you're weak and you couldn't carry it yourself, but
I can carry it by myself, and in the end we carry
it together, you helped me, I really didn't need you, I could
have done it myself, but you helped me. What's the story there?
דברי הכל חייב. Divrei hakol chayav. Everybody says חייב, chayav meaning no,
not both of them. The guy who could have done it himself.
Okay. So I'm carrying out the sofa, you want to feel like
you're helping, you help a little bit, I really didn't need you,
you're trivial, it's not a שנים שעשו, shenayim she'asu, I am the
one that really I had the ability to do it and I
did it, it seems like it's my מלאכה. melacha.
Even though I helped you.
Even though you helped. We'll see about all this in the גמרא.
Let's just get started. תניא. Tanya. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi,
we've taught similar to this: המוציא ככר לרשות הרבים חייב. Hamotzi kikar
lereshus harabim chayav.
If you took out a loaf you're חייב. chayav. הוציאו שנים, Hotziu
shenayim, if two people took it out, obviously it's a case that
anyone could have done it themselves, רבי מאיר מחייב. Rabbi Meir mechayav.
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says I don't care that two people did
it, you're still חייב, chayav. I don't buy this idea of two
people get you off the hook. רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda omer
no, אם לא יכול אחד להוציאו והוציאו שנים, im lo yachol echad
lehotzio vehotziu shenayim,
when would you be חייב chayav, if two people did it? If
one person couldn't have done it, if it was a sofa, then
חייבין, chayavin, then it's a two-person job, two people did it you're
חייב. ואם לאו, Ve'im lav, if it's not that way, if it's
like our case, a loaf of bread, and each one could have
done it, in that case פטורין, peturin, you're exempt. רבי שמעון פוטר,
Rabbi Shimon poter, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon exempts even in the sofa
case. Okay,
I guess we will end here. Tomorrow we'll pick up with what
is the source of this idea of שנים שעשו, shenayim she'asu, but
again, the three opinions are, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir doesn't believe in
שנים שעשו, shenayim she'asu, he always says you're חייב. Rabbi Yehuda says
it gets you off the hook in a case where each person
could have done it by themselves, so two people doing it is
either it's a שינוי or at least it means you can't attribute
it to me, blame that guy. That guy says don't attribute it
to me, blame the other guy. So it's no one's מלאכה melacha
in particular. And the case when they both had to do it,
when you needed two people like the sofa, so in that case
Rabbi Yehuda says you're חייב, it's a two-person job, two people did
it, it's like they did a corporate act of doing the מלאכה.
melacha. And Rabbi Shimon says even in that case you're exempt, he
exempts across the board by שנים שעשוהו. shnayim she'asuho. And right, tomorrow
we might, Michael will be taking over. Okay.
שכוייח. shkoyach. There you go.